we're continuing our discussion of Le
groups and Lee algebras in the previous
couple videos we found the Le group
matrices for rotations of spin zero spin
1/2 and spin one particles and in this
video we're going to come up with a
general procedure for finding the Le
group matrices that rotate higher spin
particles such as spin three Hales spin
two and all higher spin
particles this procedure will involve
the latter operators
we're going to see that the SO3 group
only has representations for integer
spin particles if we want to find
representations for half integer spin
particles as well we need to look at its
double cover
su2 before I talk about the procedure
with the latter operators I'm going to
be more formal about some definitions in
representation Theory because I've been
sort of glossing over them in previous
videos so I've already mentioned that a
group is a set with an operation that
obeys these four properties closure
associativity existence of an identity
element and existence of inverses Le
groups have the additional property of
being
continuous so what is the formal
definition of a representation of a
group a representation is a function row
that takes every member in a group G and
assigns it to an invertible N byn Matrix
so row is a function from the group G to
GL Ln the general linear group of
invertible n byn
matrices in order to be a representation
this function row must preserve the
group operation for all members in the
group this means that combining two
group elements and then getting its
representation Matrix is the same thing
as getting the representation matrices
for both group members and then
multiplying the matrices
a consequence of this is that the
group's identity element must be mapped
to the N byn identity
Matrix and group inverse elements must
be mapped to the corresponding
representation matrix's
inverse now with Le groups like su2 and
S SO3 the groups are defined in terms of
matrices to begin with for example su2
is defined as the set of 2x2 complex
unitary matrices with determinant one we
call these Matrix definitions the
defining representation of the group but
we can find matrices of other sizes that
satisfy the conditions of a
representation for example it's possible
to map all su2 matrices to a set of 4x4
matrices which obey all the same matrix
multiplication rules it's also possible
to map pairs of su2 matrices each to an
S SO3 Matrix
so the group s SO3 is a 3X3
representation of
su2 some of the group structure is
forgotten here because it's an
irreversible 2: one
mapping the 1ex one representation of
su2 sends all matrices to the one by one
identity
Matrix here all the group structure is
forgotten but it still technically
preserves all the multiplication
rules we can also find representations
for Lee algebras which is a function Pi
that sends Lee algebra members to n byn
matrices here the function Pi must
preserve the Le bracket of the
algebra now I mentioned we can find a
4x4 representation of the Le group
su2 but we've never seen this before how
would we go about finding this 4x4
representation well there's one way of
getting a 4x4 representation that's sort
of cheating we could take a pair of 2x2
su2 matrices and take their direct sum
which means arranging them in Block
diagonal form so that the first one
transforms the top two components of a
column and the second one transforms the
bottom two components of a column when
multiplying block diagonal matrices like
this the upper blocks will only multiply
with upper blocks and the lower blocks
will only multiply with lower blocks so
it's like we've put two independent
copies of su2 into the same
Matrix this would satisfy the
requirements of a 4x4
representation alternatively we could
take a 3X3 representation and the 1x1
representation and arrange them in Block
diagonal
form when we construct a representation
using smaller representations with the
direct sum to give a matrix in Block
diagonal form we call this
representation
reducible if a representation cannot be
written as a direct sum then we call it
an irreducible representation or IRP for
short in this video we're interested in
finding irreducible representations or
IRS so we're ignoring the case of
building representations from smaller
representations using the direct
sum we'll see later that for the su2
group there is exactly one unique
representation for a given Matrix size
we can label these representations by
The Matrix size n also called the
dimension we can also label these
representations by the Spin value which
is the dimension minus1 / 2 we're also
going to prove that the SO3 group only
has odd dimensional
representations or equivalently only
integer spin
representations
so before we learn the procedure for
building General representations of su2
we're going to spend some time studying
the 2x two or spin 1/2
representation we'll start with the spin
1/2 representation of the su2 Lee
algebra then we'll Define the ladder
operators and from there we'll
generalize the ladder operators to any
Spin and use them to build all higher
dimensional
representations we seen that one way to
get Le group matrices is to take a basis
of generators from the group's Lee
algebra and exponentiate them we know
the three 2x2 generators for su2 are
given by - one2 time pairs of Sigma
matrices these give a basis for 2x two
traceless anti-mission
matrices I'm now going to introduce the
raising and lowering operators G+ and G
minus which are also called ladder
operators recall that the spin up
spinner state is represented by the
column
1 and the spin down spinner state is
represented by the column
01 we'll Define the raising operator as
changing the down state into the UP
State and changing the UP State into the
zero spinner we'll Define the lowering
operator as changing the UP State into
the down state and changing the down
state into the Z
spinner the raising operator G+ is given
by The Matrix 01 0 0 and the lowering
operator G minus is given by The Matrix
001 0 you can see they obey the expected
properties given the su2 generators to
build G+ we can split it into symmetric
and anti-symmetric parts then if we pull
out a factor of I we can can see that we
can rewrite G+ as I * g y z minus g z
x we can do something similar with G
minus to write it as I * g y z plus g z
x I'm going to Define one last operator
gz when this acts on the UP State it
returns plus one2 time the UP State when
it acts on the down state it returns
min-2 times the down
state in other words the up and down
states are I vectors of the gz operator
with I values +2 and minus
one2 in this basis the gz Matrix would
be diagonal with entries + 1/2 and
min-2 this Matrix is simply equal to I *
gxy also it's very common to label the
up and down States after their igen Val
values under
gz so the UP State could be labeled with
plus2 and the down state could be
labeled with minus
one2 this is related to why we call the
2x two representation the spin 1/2
representation the reason I'm calling
this Matrix gz is because this is the
Matrix physicists use when measuring the
spin angular momentum of a particle
along the Z AIS or equivalently the XY
plane
it's also worth noting that since gxy is
anti-mission then gz must be Herm
Mission this implies all the ion vectors
of gz are
orthogonal so the ion vectors of gz give
us an orthogonal
basis so using our original su2 basis
we've defined three new operators the
raising operator G plus the lowering
operator G minus and the I value
operator
gz note that since we Define these
raising and lowering operators using
complex coefficients this means we are
leaving the su2 Lee algebra and going to
its complexified
version also since most physics
textbooks use Herm Mission matrices for
the su2 generators you might find the
definition of these operators look a
little different but they behave the
same
way now let's look at the com mutators
of these three matrices to help compute
these I'm going to look at some
properties of the commutator the
commutator of matrices X and Y is x y -
YX notice that if we swap the order of
the commutator inputs we get a negative
sign compared to the original
commutator this also means the
commutator of any Matrix with itself is
always zero since the two terms
cancel now let's look at linearity
properties let's say we have matrices XY
Z and scaling numbers A and B and we
want to determine the commutator of Zed
and ax + b y we can write out the
commutator as the subtraction of the two
products after Distributing we can
factor out a from the Z and X terms and
Factor B from The Zed and Y terms these
then become the Z x and z y
commutators so what we've learned here
is that the second input in the
commutator bracket is linear we can
either add and scale matrices inside the
commutator input or ADD and scale the
commutators of the individual matrices
and get the same
result the first input of the commutator
also obeys the linearity property so we
say the commutator is
bilinear I'm now going to compute the
the commutator of G+ and G minus you can
pause now if you want to try it
yourself first we Sub in their
definitions and then use linearity rules
once and then twice to get four terms
the commutator of a term with itself is
always zero so the first and fourth
terms go to
zero we can put the factors of I out in
front and swap the order of the inputs
in the first remaining commutator if we
change its sign
we end up with 2 I * the commutator of g
y z and G ZX which we know is
gxy and using the definition of gz this
gives us 2
gz you can also pause and try to
calculate the commutator of gz and G+
with the answer being
G+ and calculating the commutator of gz
and G minus the answer ends up being
negative G minus
so we have this new basis of the
complexified Lee algebra
su2 and this gives us a new set of
commutators so what was the point of
this change of
basis well we know gz acting on the plus
1/2 State gives I Value Plus one2 and GZ
acting on the minus one2 State gives an
igen value of
min-2 we can summarize this by saying gz
acting on the M State gives an I value
of
M but what happens if we have gz acting
on the state G+ * the M State we can
take the product gz * G+ and see it in
this commutation relation this means we
can replace it with the commutator of gz
and G+ added with G+ *
gz we know from previous slides that
this commutator just gives
G+ and when gz X on the M state it gives
the IG value M we can then factor out G+
from these terms and get M +1 out in
front what this means is that we can
treat G+ * the M State as a new igen
Vector of the gz operator and it has I
value m +
one this makes sense given what we
expect from the raising operator it
should raise us from the minus one2
state to the Plus 1/ half State thereby
increasing the igen value by
one now recall that the G+ operator will
send the vector with the highest igen
value to zero this is true in the 2x2
representation but it's true in any
finite dimensional
representation because we'll eventually
run out of basis vectors to Rays at some
point we call the basis Vector that G+
sends to zero the vector with the
highest igen value we sometimes call
igen values weights in this context so
this is also called the IG Vector with
the highest
weight we can do something similar with
the lowering operator G minus except
this time the commutator gives negative
G minus and so we end up with an IG
value of M
minus1 again this makes sense we expect
the lowering operator to decrease the IG
value of a state by one
except in the case of the lowest IG
value or lowest weight Vector which gets
sent to
zero it turns out that if the highest IG
value is J then the lowest IG value will
be minus J I'll prove this a bit later
in the
video so let's think carefully about
what we've just seen with these igen
value relations thinking in terms of any
Dimension not just the 2x two
representation when we applied gz to the
state G+ on M we got an IG value of m +
1 so this means that the G+ on M State
behaves like the state m + one however
since the state appears on both sides of
the equation we have only showed that G+
on M is proportional to the state M +1
they are not necessarily equal they're
only equal up to some scaling Factor
Alpha similarly with the G minus k
the state G minus on M behaves like the
state M minus1 and is proportional
According to some proportionality
constant
beta now to solve for Alpha and beta I'm
going to make the assumptions that the
igen vectors of gz that we're working
with are all normalized so the broet
inner product of any gz I Vector with
itself always equals
1 to get the norm of G+ on M we use a
its corresponding bra Vector which is
its hermiss conjugate this equals the
bra version of M * G Plus
dagger now let's take their inner
product we know G+ raises the state to m
+ 1 with a proportionality constant
Alpha for the Kat Vector G Plus dagger
should do the same thing on the bra
Vector but it gives the proportionality
constant of alpha complex conjugate
Instead This is is because the Herm
Mission conjugate of a scaler is just
the complex
conjugate putting the scalers out in
front Alpha conjugate time Alpha is just
the squared magnitude of Alpha and since
these State vectors are normalized we
just get
one so we've shown that the squared Norm
of the G+ onm state is the magnitude of
alpha squared we can similarly show that
the squared Norm of the G minus onm
state is the magnitude of beta
squ so let's calculate G+ D or G+ by
plugging in its definition we can pass
the dagger to all the terms inside the
brackets which also flips the sign of
the complex I if we distribute the four
terms we can write minus I * I as
1 now we know all the su2 generators are
anti-mission so the dagger operation
just gives a minus
sign with what's left we get g y z^ 2us
g z x^ 2 - I * this commutator which we
know is just
gxy and we know I * gxy is the
definition of our ion value operator
gz we can do a similar calculation for G
minus dag or G minus the only difference
is that gz has a plus sign instead of a
minus sign so we have these two
formulas
to understand these formulas better I'm
going to talk about the Kazmir operator
g s which is defined as the negative
squares of the su2 generators summed
together g^ s is important because it
commutes with everything in the Lee
algebra this G squ operator is not a
member of the Lee algebra su2 because
the Lee algebra doesn't understand what
squaring matrices means Lee Al albas
only understand the Lee bracket or
commutator the Kazmir operator g^ s
instead lives in the universal
enveloping algebra but I'm not going to
talk about that in this
video to prove that g squared commutes
with everything I'm going to go over a
couple more properties of the commutator
first the commutator of a with a squ
always goes to zero because the two
terms cancel also the commutator obeys a
kind of product rule if we take the
commutator of a with B * C we can
subtract and add b a c in the middle and
get a sum of two commutators one with b
and one with
C using this we can prove gxy commutes
with g^ s we can write out the
definition of g^ s and then distribute
we know the commutator involving only
gxy goes to zero automatically
the other two terms can be evaluated
using product rule giving two terms
each we can rewrite these commutators as
gzx and gy Z working out the signs all
the terms cancel and we see the
commutator goes to
zero we can use similar proofs to show
that g^ s commutes with the other two
basis vectors and so commutes with every
element of
su2 so knowing the defition definition
of g^ s and also the gz operator we can
move GX y^ 2 over to the other side and
rewrite it in terms of
gz finally we can take the G+ and G
minus formulas from before and rewrite
the gy Z and g z x Parts using g^ S and
GZ
instead so now these products are
written entirely in terms of G ^2 and
GZ so what does this casm Operator g^ 2
give when it acts on the vector M well
let's take M to be the highest weight
Vector labeled J remember this is the
vector that G+ sends to zero so if we
apply g^ 2 to the highest weight Vector
J the G+ acting on the vector J will
immediately go to zero and GZ will
simply return the I value J so gz^ 2 +
gz just gives us j s + J which can be
Rewritten as J * J +
1 so knowing this let's use the lowering
operator to see how g^ 2 acts on the J
minus1 Vector we can replace the J
minus1 Vector with G minus acting on the
J Vector divided by Beta however since
g^ 2 commutes with all the other G's we
can flip their order and get it to act
on the J Vector giving J * J + 1
we can then use the lowering operator to
return the J state to the jus1
state so because g^ 2 commutes with
everything it also returns J * J + 1
when acting on the J minus1 vector and
by induction G ^2 returns J * J + 1 on
all other igen vectors of
gz when a representation has highest
weight J we call it the spin J
representation this is why the 2x2
representation is called the spin 1/2
representation so we can finally compute
what this G+ dagger G+ gives when acting
on the M Vector the g^ 2 part gives us J
* J +
1 and the minus g z^ 2 minus g z part
gives us m^2 minus M which can be
Rewritten as M * m + 1
plugging this into our formula for Alpha
we can pull all the scalar Parts out in
front send the norm of M to one since
it's normalized and take the square root
of this formula to get
Alpha technically Alpha could be a
complex number with a complex phase but
we can choose a phase convention where
Alpha is always a real
number we can do something similar for G
minus where the only difference is a
minus sign in the formula here and this
gives us a formula for
beta so finally we now have the formulas
for the alpha and beta coefficients for
the raising and lowering operators and
these work in any
Dimension I'm going to point out that in
the alpha formula if we plug in m equal
J we get zero this means that G+ cannot
raise the J state so J is the highest
igen value or highest weight
similarly for beta if we plug in M =
minus J we get Zer so G minus cannot
lower the minus J state so minus J is
the lowest igen value or lowest weight
this means that in a given
representation the basis Vector weights
range from plus J to minus J in
increments of
one this means that the highest weight J
must be an integer or half integer
otherwise increments of one would mean
that the highest and lowest weights
would have different magnitudes instead
of equaling plus JN minus J which is
required this also means that the
dimension size n of the representation
is always equal to 2J + 1 for spin J
since a highest weight of J implies
there are 2J + 1 basis I
vectors so we've covered a lot over the
course of this video video we started
with the three generators in the su2 Lee
algebra then we changed basis to G+ G
minus and GZ and determined their
commutation
relations we also found these igen value
relations for The Operators and we saw
G+ and G minus raise and lower the igen
vector States according to the
proportionality factors Alpha and beta
and we determined these formulas for the
various Alpha and and beta coefficients
which depend on their representation
spin number J and a vector's I value
M now in the case of the 2x two
representation none of this gives us any
new results that we didn't know before
the alpha and betas just end up being
one but the important fact here is that
the truth of these formulas does not
depend on the dimension of the
representation we can use these formulas
for the spin one case of 3x3 matrices
the spin 3 haves case of 4x4 matrices
the Spin 2 case of 5x5 matrices and so
on let's try using all of this to build
up the 3X3 spin one
representation here we'll have three
basis State vectors which I'm going to
label as + one 0 and minus
one the highest weight here is + one so
this is the spin value J
also keep in mind this Vector labeled
with zero is not the zero Vector it's
just the label we're giving to this
particular basis Vector with igen value
zero for the spin one case we know that
J equals 1 so J * J + 1 =
2 now let's calculate these
proportionality constants for the
raising and lowering
operators for G+ acting on the minus one
state we subit M = -1 and get a constant
of theare < TK of 2 and here the state
is raised to the zero state for G+
acting on the Zero State we Sub in m
equals 0 and we get a constant of the
square < TK of two next to the one
state we can also check that G+ acting
on the one state goes to zero but this
is expected since there are only three
basis vectors and we can't raise the
highest weight Vector to a higher
one we can also apply G minus to the
three states to get coefficients of the
square roots of two except in the minus
one state case where we get zero since
we can't lower it
anymore recall for a given Matrix we can
get one of its entries using the
appropriate row Vector on the left to
select a row and the appropriate column
Vector on the right to select a column
this out puts the scaler entry for that
row and
column we can do the same thing for our
3x3 G+ Matrix and get all nine of its
entries using the various bras and Cs on
either side most of the entries go to
zero but a couple of them end up being
the square root of two these entries are
used to raise the various State igen
vectors we can do something similar with
the G minus operator to get this 3 3x3
Matrix and also the gz Matrix but that's
pretty obvious since all the igen values
are already on the
diagonal now that we have matrices for
G+ G minus and GZ we can use our change
of basis equations to change back to the
standard basis for generators of 3D
rotations these indeed give traceless
anti-mission matrices that we would
expect from the su2 Lee algebra
now this is a different 3x3 solution
than the one we've seen in previous
videos but we can switch between these
new ones and the more familiar 3x3
solution just by using a change of
coordinates the two solutions are
equivalent now if we want to see the
spin one representation of the su2 group
we just exponentiate the generator
matrices in the Lee algebra to get these
rotation matrices in the Lee group
okay so we saw that for the spin one
representation of su2 the procedure was
to calculate the proportionality
constants then get G+ G minus and GZ as
matrices then switch back to the
standard basis and get the su2 Le
algebra generators we can then
exponentiate them to get the su2 Le
group
matrices we can use this same procedure
again for the spin 3 half representation
of su2 which uses 4x4
matrices the four basis vectors would
then be labeled with igen values plus
three Hales + 1/2 - 1/2 and -
3es the highest weight is three Hales so
this is the spin 3es
representation I'd encourage you to
pause the video and try finding the spin
three haves su2 Lee algebra
representation before I give the
answer calculating the the
proportionality constants is a bit more
involved this time but for gz we get the
square < TK of 3 2 and the square < TK
of 3 and for G minus we get similar
results this gives us the following G+ G
minus and GZ
matrices changing basis we get these 4x4
generators while exponentiating the gxy
generator is easy exponentiating the
other generators is trickier so I'm not
going to do it in this
video I'll also show you the 5x5
solution for Spin 2 so pause now if you
want to
try the G Plus proportionality constants
are 2 the square < TK of 6 the square <
TK of 6 and 2 and same for G minus and
we get these matrices for G+ G minus and
GZ and we can change bases to get these
generators exponentiating the gxy gener
generator we easily get a 5x5 su2 group
Matrix for doing rotations in the XY
plane in the convention used in this
video the XY generators and group
matrices are always
diagonal let's take a look at how some
particles rotate in the XY plane under
the su2 group spin zero particles
transform with an identity Matrix so
they don't change under
rotations for spin 1/2 particles we get
two states the spin up and spin down
States whose complex coefficients change
in opposite directions under this
rotation it's also worth noting that the
1/2 coefficients in the exponents mean
the period of rotation is two full turns
or 4
Pi for spin one particles we get three
states the plus one and minus one States
correspond to two classical waves that
are left and right polarized around the
Zed AIS and they take a full turn of 2
pi to get back to their starting point
the zero State corresponds to the
longitudinal polarization along the Zed
AIS which does not change when we rotate
around the Zed AIS so it transforms with
the constant
one for massless spin one particles that
travel at the speed of light like
photons the longitudinal polarization is
not possible so we only have the + one
and minus1
states for spin 3 half particles we get
four states the plus andus one/ half
states have a period of two full turns
but the plus and minus three half states
have a period of 2/3 of a full turn
however overall the states collectively
have a period of two full turns or 4 Pi
for spin two particles we get five state
States the zero state is constant under
these rotations the plus and minus one
states have a period of one full turn
and the plus and minus two states have a
period of half a full turn collectively
the states have a period of one full
turn or 2 pi for massless spin two
particles that travel at the speed of
light like the hypothetical graviton the
inner three states are not possible so
we only have the plus two and minus 2
States classically gravitational waves
come in two
polarizations the plus and cross
polarizations where the amplitudes move
in and out along the directions of plus
and cross shapes the plus two and minus
2 States correspond to specific linear
combinations of the plus and cross
polarizations these polarizations come
back to themselves after half a full
turn so their period is half of 2 pi
now it can be confusing to tell the
difference between the plus one state
from the spin one representation and the
plus one state from the Spin 2
representation for this reason we often
include the spin number J as a prefix
label on the igen states this helps us
keep track of which igen Vector belongs
to which
representation now it's a fact that
there is exactly one IR reducible
representation of su2 per Dimension if
you find two different IRS of the same
size you can always swap between them
using a change of
coordinates this happens because every
su2 Lee algebra EP allows us to define
the latter operators and assuming a
finite dimensional representation there
will always be a highest weight Vector J
we can then use the lowering operator to
create an orthogonal basis for this
IR so if we have two su2 Lee algebra IRS
of the same Dimension pi and Pi Tilda
each with different generators we can
always use their respective lad
operators to Define an orthogonal basis
for each
representation we can then use a change
of basis Matrix C to swap between these
two bases this means we can also change
bases for any linear map L and so we can
always swap between the two su2
generators using the same change of
coordinates Matrix
C the group representations of su2 also
use the same change of coordinate Matrix
C to change representations because of
the properties of Matrix
exponentials so we know that su2 has
exactly one irreducible representation
per Dimension now we'll prove that SO3
has only one reducible representation
for every odd Dimension this is a
consequence of su2 being the double
cover of
S3 to prove this we'll list a few
facts an important fact to remember is
that a representation map row will
always send the identity element of a
group to the N byn identity
Matrix this is required to preserve the
group multiplication
rules now the double cover map 5 from
su2 to SO3 sends the plus and minus
versions of a given su2 Matrix to the
same s SO3 Matrix r as a result the
double cover map F sends both the
positive and negative 2x2 identity
Matrix to the 3X3 identity
Matrix now if we have an irreducible
representation row of s SO3 if we
combine it with the double covering map
fi this AO automatically gives us an
irreducible representation Sigma of
su2 since F sends the negative identity
to the identity Matrix and row sends the
identity to the identity this means the
induced map Sigma sends the negative
identity in su2 to the identity
Matrix now let's look at the 4x4 and 5x5
IRS of
su2 we know there's only one EP per
Dimension and we already know that this
2x2 diagonal matrix gets sent to this
4x4 and 5x5 diagonal matrix
respectively now let's set Theta to 2 pi
all the exponents with a half integer
next to the angle will get sent to -1
since e to the I Pi * an odd number is
-1 and all the exponentials with
integers next to the angle will get sent
to + one since e to the i 2 pi * an
integer = +
1 so in the 4x4 ep the negative identity
gets sent to the negative identity and
in the 5x5 ep the negative identity gets
sent to the positive
identity more generally for every even
dimensional or half integer spin ep the
negative identity is sent to the
negative identity but for odd
dimensional or integer spin ARS the
negative identity is sent to the posit
postive
identity okay let's bring this all
together we have the double cover map
five from su2 to SO3 which sends the -2
X2 identity to the 3X3 identity and if
we have an N byn irreducible
representation of s SO3 this will send
the 3X3 identity to the N byn identity
as required by the rules of
representations this also induces an N
byn irreducible representation Sigma of
su2 which is the composition of fi and
the S SO3 ere as a result this Sigma
always Maps the - 2x2 identity to the N
byn
identity now let's include the
information from the last slide if the
dimension n is odd the N byn EP of su2
will send the negative identity to the
positive identity this is consistent
with what we have above so there are no
problems
but if the dimension n is even the N byn
EP of su2 sends the negative identity to
the negative identity this contradicts
what we have above the only conclusion
we can draw is that there are no n byn
irreducible representations of SO3 for
even dimensional n if there was Sigma
would always send the negative identity
to the positive identity which is not
the case for even dimensional EPS of
su2 so we've proven that s SO3 only has
IRS in odd Dimensions or equivalently
for integer
spins now I'd like to move on to space
time but before I do I want to point out
that it's possible to Define
representations for su2 using polinomial
and derivative operators like this these
Obey the expected commutation relations
for
su2 we can prove this using these
identities and various commutator
properties that we've seen
before I don't know if these have an
official name but we could call them
polom or differential
representations in quantum mechanics
these are usually defined with IH in
front and they generate rotation
operations on Wave
functions now we know that su2 has one
irreducible representation per Dimension
but we know from from the last video
that SL2 C in space time has two
non-equivalent 2x two irreducible
representations which we call the left
and right
representations we cannot change between
these representations using a change of
coordinates we know that with the su2
Lee algebra if we complexify it with
complex coefficients we can Define the
raising and lowering operators which
lets us Define a representation highest
weight or spin
value with the SL2 C Le algebra if we
complexify it we can break it up into
the direct sum of a pair of complexified
su2 Le algebras each with their own spin
values so a given SL2 C representation
is defined by a pair of spin values
instead of just
one we saw this trick of breaking up
complexified SL l2c into a pair of
complexified S2s in the last video so
let's see how this
works we start by taking the SL 2C
rotation and boost generators the J's
and the K's and change bases to the A's
and
B's the only difference between the A's
and B's is the sign in front of the K
boost
generators these form two separate
copies of the su2 Lee algebra
which commute with each
other if we take each su2 copy and
complexify it so that they have complex
coefficients we can Define raising and
lowering operators and igen value
operators in each su2 copy this means we
can label each su2 representation with
the highest weight or spin
value so this means that to label a
given irreducible representation of SL
to C we need to pick two spin values we
refer to the first spin value as left
and the Second Spin value where the sign
in front of the boosts is reversed is
called right these spin values are often
written in an ordered pair like
this so for su2 irreducible
representations we get a one dimensional
list of spin
values but for SL2 C irreducible
represent ations we get a
two-dimensional grid which contains all
possible pairs of left and right spin
values if we move from the Lee algebra
SL2 C to the Le group SL2 C the EPS are
also labeled by a pair of spin values
this time the EPS can be written as the
tensor product of a left representation
and a right
representation we get a similar 2D table
of eps for for the Le group SL2 C this
contains the representations which
transform scalers left and right vile
Spinners as well as SpaceTime
vectors I'm not going to go into much
more detail here because the next video
will be all about the tensor products of
representations direct Spinners
transform with the direct sum of the
left and right spin 1/2
representations so this is a reducible
represent
presentation